嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程, 那么上期
my name is Cherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series, so last time
实际上, 在前几期, 我们把所有的OpenGL代码都提取到类中了
and in fact over the last few episodes, we've been extracting all of our OpenGL code away into classes
这样我们处理它们就会更容易一点
so that we can deal with them a little bit more easily
当真正需要编写真正的图形代码的时候
when it actually comes time to writing real graphics code
我们今天还是继续抽象着色器吧
and today we're going to continue that journey with shaders
那么我们已经做完了的, 比如顶点缓冲区和顶点数组
so we've done like vertex buffers and vertex arrays
以及像顶点缓冲区布局之类的
and like vertex buffer layout and all that kind of stuff
并且现在, 下一步就是着色器
and now, the next step is going to be shaders
那么我们来看看, 我们实际要如何来抽象着色器
so let's take a look at, how we can actually abstract shader
好吧, 首先, 让我们来说说, 那么
well, first of all, let's just talk about it, so
我马上要抽象这个的方法是比较简单的
the way that I'm going to abstract this right now is in a simple way
因为着色器, 当处理着色器的时候
because shaders, when it comes to shaders
顺便说一下, 如果你们不知道着色器是什么
and if you guys don't know what a shader is, by the way
一定要去看看我制作的关于着色器的视频
definitely check out the video that I made about shader
但是着色器是一个非常复杂的主题
but shader are an incredibly complex topic
对于图形编程或任意的渲染操作, 着色器都是非常非常重要的
and shaders are very very important to graphics programming or any kind of rendering
对吧, 因此, 这比较倾向于
right, and so because of that, there tends to be
就像倾向于创建一个相当复杂的系统
like a tendency to actually make a rather complicated system
这不仅易于使用, 而且在游戏和游戏引擎中也非常强大
that is both easy to use, but also extremely powerful in games and game engines typically
有一种自定义的着色语言是非常常见的
it's very common to have a custom shading language
然后为每种渲染接口或平台编译成着色器代码
which then compiles into shader code for each kind of rendering api or platform
在运行时, 它也是通过代码来控制和扩展的, 这意味着
and also is somewhat kind of controllable and extensible through the code at runtime, meaning that
实际生成新的着色器对于游戏非常常见, 然后
it's very common for games to actually generate new shaders, and then
让它们用于渲染, 当游戏实际运行的时候
have them be used for rendering while the game is actually running
或者在游戏正在加载之类的时候, 对吧
or while the game is loading or something like that, right
着色器生成和这种动态创建是非常非常常见的
shader generation and shader kind of creation on the fly is something that's very very common
并且总的来说, 整个就像兔子洞一样
and in general, the whole like rabbit hole of
让我们为我们的引擎编写一个着色器系统, 这是一个非常庞大的主题
let's write a shader system for our engine, like tends to be such a massive topic
并且我们肯定不会
and we're definitely not
甚至在今天或整个OpenGL系列中, 我们都只涉及到皮毛
even going to scratch the surface today or in this entire OpenGL series
因为, 坦白地说吧, 这与OpenGL渲染无关
because it's irrelevant, quite frankly to actually OpenGL rendering
当我们认为着色器是OpenGL部分的时候, 就像没有任何东西
when we think about shader is an OpenGL, like there's nothing to it
只需要将文本写入文件或作为一个字符串
you just write text in a file or as a string
就完事了, 就好像我刚才描述的那些东西都没有真正的需要
and you're done, like there's no real need for any of the stuff that I just described
那些东西通常在真正的游戏引擎会用到, 对吧
that kind of stuff is typically used by an actual game engine, right
我们不会在这个只关于OpenGL的系列中讨论那个
and we're not talking about that in this series, this is just about OpenGL
之后, 当我制作游戏引擎系列时
later on, when I make the game engine series
我们肯定就会讨论那个东西
we will definitely talk about that stuff
我们肯定会实现一种更复杂的着色器和材质系统之类的
we'll definitely implement a way more complicated shader and material system and all of that
在那个系列中
in that series
所以我只想和在这儿的各位保持一致
so I just want to just want to be on the same page as everyone else here
对于我们今天真正想要达到的目标
as to what we're actually trying to achieve today
因为我绝不会试着去写一个疯狂的着色器系统或类似的东西
because by no means am I trying to rate trying to write a crazy shader system or anything like that
对吧, 我今天在这儿要做的就是
right, here all I'm doing today is
我想要把我们写过的所有OpenGL着色器代码
I want to basically take all of the OpenGL shader code that we've written
从接口里面抽象出来, 这很容易使用, 明白吧
abstract that out behind an api, that's really easy to use, understand
并保持我们的实际用户或客户端代码非常简洁
and keeps our actual kind of user or client side code really concise
这样在这个系列中, 当涉及到用图形做一些非常疯狂的事情的时候
so that when it comes time to and do really crazy things with graphics in this series
实际上, 对你来说, 阅读代码就会很容易
it's actually going to be easy for you to read the actual code
因为这将是一个高层次的相对的概念
because it's going to be high level and fairly conceptual
并不像你知道的, 统一变量, 矩阵和4fv
and not like you know, gl_uniform, matrix, 4fv
或者不管函数名可能是什么, 对吧
or whatever the function names might be, right
这处理起来就会很简单
it's going to be very simple to deal with
希望至少这是我的目标, 所以说
hopefully at least that's my goal for this, so that being said
我们需要在着色器代码中抽象什么
what is it that we actually need to need to abstract in our shader code
对吧, 或者它是什么
right, or what it is
我们并没有做什么特别疯狂的事
we haven't done anything particularly too crazy
我的意思是我们正在从一个文件中加载一个着色器
I mean we're loading a shader from a file
根据我现在读到的源代码
based on the source code that I'm reading right now
然后渲染它
and we're rendering it
我认为它可能有一个设置的类似统一变量的一些东西
and I think it might have a uniform something like that that we're setting
是的, 我们要给那个颜色的fa设置一个统一变量
yeah, we're setting a uniform for fa with the color
我认为我们的, 对, 矩形或正方形的颜色
I think of our, yes, with the color of our rectangle or our square
这就是我们所做的
that's all that we're doing
但是一般来说, 着色器需要什么, 首先
but in general, what does the shaders is need, well first of all
我们基本上希望能够传递一个文件或一个字符串
we want to be able to basically pass in a file or a string
把它作为着色器来编译, 所以那就是第一步
and have that be compiled as a shader, so that's kind of step one
我们希望能够绑定和解绑定着色器, 这是第二步
we want to be able to bind and unbind the shader, step two and
第三步就是我们需要能够设置
step three is we want to be able to set
着色器中各种不同的统一变量, 对吧
the uniforms all of the different uniforms for the shader, okay
这可能就是我们现在正在研究的东西
that's probably it for something that we're looking at right now
我的意思是, 就像读取属性
I mean, like reading back attributes, reading back
就像能够在一个着色器中载入, 然后询问着色器
like being able to load in a shader, and then ask the shader
嘿, 你实际有什么统一变量
hey, what uniforms do you actually have
它们是什么类型, 所有那些都是非常有用的东西
and what types are they, and all of that is something that would be incredibly useful
但那可能更多地属于游戏引擎的着色器系统
but again that probably falls more into a shader system for a game engine
那实际上需要暂停着色器源代码等等
and that would actually require pausing the shader source code and all that
这样超出作用域会花很长时间
this way out of the scopes can take way too long
反正我现在也不感兴趣
and not something I'm interested in right now anyway
我的意思是, 对于这个系列
for this series, I mean
但是, 我的意思是, 我们只想能够创建着色器, 绑定它们, 拿来使用
but yeah, I mean we just want to be able to create shader, bind them, for use
也设置统一变量, 就这些
and also set uniforms, that's it
那么, 让我们开始深入并开始重构源码吧
so let's dive in and start refactoring the source code
因此我们可以做所有这些
so that we can do all of that
好了, 所以第一步, 在src目录下, 添加一个新项
okay, so step one, under src, let's add a new item
添加一个头文件, 就叫Shader
I'm gonna add a header file, it's gonna be called Shader
也创建一个cpp文件Shader, 好了
and I'm going to do the same thing for a cpp file, okay
cpp文件当然会包含头文件
cpp file of course is going to include the header file
让我们返回头文件开始编辑它, 那么就是class Shader
and let's go back to the header file and start editing it, so class Shader
我们将会有一些私有和公共的东西
we're just going to have a few pop private and public things here
有一个构造方法, 接收一个const std::string& filename
we'll have a constructor, which takes in a const std::string& filename
我上次做了什么, 或上次没做什么
now what I did do last time or not last time
但在实际的着色器那期, 我最终是在Application文件中做的
but in the actual shader episode, what I actually ended up doing was inside Application
我确实做了它, 这样我们就可以在一个文件中写我们的着色器
I did actually make it, so that we could write our shader in one file
因为我觉得要处理两个文件很烦人
because I find it very annoying having to do with two files
所以你可以看到这里, 我们实际上有
so you can see that over here, we actually have
一个独立文件中有两种类型的节点, 片段着色器和顶点着色器
a single file with two kind of sections, shader of fragment and shader of vertex
那非常重要
that's very important
那也意味着我们不需要接收
that also means that we don't need to be able to take in kind of well
我们不需要接收两个不同的文件
we don't need to take in two different files
我们只需要输入文件路径, 一切就都好了
we can just take in the file path, and everything will be okay
那么就是filepath, 我们会有一个析构方法
so filepath, we're going to have a destructor
我们将有Bind方法, 它将是一个常量方法
we're going to have Bind, which is going to be a const function
还有Unbind方法, 当然, 在OpenGL中, 我们会绑定
and Unbind, now of course with OpenGL, we kind of bind
顶点数组和顶点缓冲区, 我们也会绑定
vertex arrays and we bind vertex buffers, and we bind
比如索引缓冲区纹理或者之类的东西
like index buffers or textures or all that stuff
但在着色程序中, 它被称为glUseProgram
but with shader programs, it's called glUseProgram
既然我们创建了这个接口
now since we're making this api though
我们就需要保持一致, 我们会把它称为绑定, 对于一切
we're gonna be consistent, and we're gonna call it bind, for everything
所以这个就是Bind, 然后我们也有Unbind
so this is gonna be Bind, and then we've gonna have Unbind
就是那样, 当然, 那和顶点缓冲区是一致的
and that is, of course, consistent with things like our vertex buffer
那个也有Bind和Unbind
which also have a Bind and Unbind
好了, 最后我还需要设置统一变量
all right, and then finally I want to be able to also set uniforms
现在这儿有许多这些
now there are so many of these
再说一次, 我没有尝试创建一个复杂的着色器系统
and again, I'm not trying to create a complicated shader system
所以我不需要创建
so I don't want to make something
一些模板化的东西, 然后需要实际处理它自己的东西
that's templated and then has to actually deal with its own kind of things
如果我把它写成我的引擎的代码或者类似的东西
if I was writing this as actual kind of code for my engine or something like that
我肯定会有一个SetValue或SetUniform方法
I would definitely just probably have a SetValue or SetUniform function
这是模板化的, 甚至不止模板化
that was kind of templated and not even templated
但也像在一个更复杂的着色器系统中
but also like in a more complicated shader system
实际上你可以直接传入着色器源码去计算出
you would actually just pass the shader source code to work out
一个统一变量的类型是什么
what type a uniform variable was
通过实现那个, 你就可以验证其中的内容, 也可以设计一个接口
and by doing that, you can validate kind of what goes into it, and also design an api
这样你就有SetValue方法了
so that you can just have SetValue
你所需要的只是名称和值
and all you need is the name and the value
它会自动设置正确的数据等等
and it will automatically set the right data and all of that
这是我想在游戏引擎系列中讨论的内容
something worth everything I want to talk about in the game engine series
但我们暂时只是想让这段代码非常简单
but for now we're just trying to keep this code really straightforward really simple
这样再说一次, 当我们在OpenGL中做东西时
so that again, when we actually get into making things in OpenGL
读起来很容易
it's gonna be easy to read
人们不需要说, 哇, 这真是一个复杂的系统
and people won't have to be like, wow, this is such a complicated system
为什么要构建那样的东西
why built something like that
或者关于这个, 就没啥意义
or I doesn't make any sense for this
所以记住那个就好
so just keep that in mind
那么我们可能需要一个SetUniform4f之类的方法
so we're gonna have like a SetUniform4f or something like that
这只是模仿我们之前的那个
which is just going to mimic our initial one
随着我们继续深入还会添加其他的方法
and it will add the other ones as we go along
那么这个, 当然不得不需要一个const std::string& name
so this of course is going to have to have a const std::string& name
并且之后就是几个浮点数
and then a float
就是值的四个浮点数, 就是v0, v1
and then four floats for the value, so we'll just have v0, v1
如果我有一个需要接入的数学库
if I had a math library which we need to get on to
可能就会在这儿使用那个了
I would probably just use that here
我的意思是就像一个vec4, 好了, 那么我们继续
like I mean like a vec4, okay, so there we go
我想差不多就这样了
and then I think that's pretty much it
那么在私有属性方面
so in terms of private
我们这儿需要的就是一个unsigned int m_RendererID
what we need here is an unsigned int m_RendererID
然后我们马上还会有一些缓存统一变量的属性
and then we're also going to have some kind of caching system in a minute for uniforms
并且你马上就会知道为什么了
and you'll find out why in a minute
在这儿下面也会有一个私有方法
I'll also have a private function down here
我想就是unsigned int GetUniformLocation()
which is going to be an unsigned int I think GetUniformLocation
那个也需要接收一个参数const std::string& name
and that's going to take in a const std::string& name as well
用来获取我们OpenGL的统一变量的位置
that's going to be used to retrieve our OpenGL uniform locations
好了, 右键点击这里使用可视化辅助工具
alright, right click here and then using visual assist
创建方法的实现
I'll create method implementations
这儿也要包含string
I'm also going to include string here
因为这让我有点难过
because it's getting a little bit sad at me
很好, 回到这里, 让我们开始补充这些东西, 现在为了调试
okay, cool, so back over here, let's start filling all this stuff out, now for debug purposes
实际上也要保存那个filepath, 这样我们就可以打印
I am I am actually going to also save that filepath, just so that we can print out
比如着色器所属的文件是什么, 如果我们需要的话
like what what file a shader belongs to, if we need to
那么我就在这儿设置那个吧, 就是m_FilePath(filepath)
so I'll just set that up here, and m_FilePath(filepath)
也需要设置m_RendererID(0)
I'm also going to assign m_RenererID to 0
然后我要创建一个叫CompileShader的方法
and then I'm going to write a function called CompileShader and
这正是另一个私有方法, 就是void CompileShader()
this is just going to be another private function here void CompileShader
我们可能需要返回false或其他类型
we might want to return false or something
我可能实际把返回数据类型设置为bool, 然后才是CompileShader
I might actually make this a boolean, and then CompileShader
让我们来看看这里
let's go over here
就在析构方法下面创建它
I'll make it just beneath the destructor
当然, 我就叫它CompileShader
and I'll call it CompileShader, of course
Shader::, 它实际返回一个bool, 好了, 酷
Shader, and it's actually a bool, all right, cool
那么就是CompileShader, 当我们返回Application文件中的代码
so CompileShader, if we go back to our Application code
我们已经写了所有这些代码, 但它正在重构
we've already written all this code, but it's refactoring it
所以这里就是CreateShader的代码
so here's the CreateShader code
已经有了一个顶点着色器和一个片段着色器
that already has a vertex shader and a fragment shader
这是很酷的, 我要用所有这些
which is cool, I'm just going to take all of this
说实话, 就是复制这整个函数,
and in fact, this entire function, copy it
把它粘贴在这儿, 现在我会让它成为一个静态方法
and when I put it here, now I could leave it a static
因为它真的不会改变
because it's really not going to change
但我马上就会重构它成为一个实际的成员
but I will reflect it in a minute to be an actual member
然后我想这个就是我们的CompileShader方法
and then this I think is our CompileShader function
就我尝试在这儿创建的方法
which I tried to make here
但明显的是, 我忘了那个实际在这儿创建的方法
but obviously, I forgot that I actually had it here
然后这个就是我们的ParseShader
and then this is our ParseShader
把这些都弄清楚
which just figures that stuff out
所以我只是将Application文件中所有主要的内容复制到这里
so really I'm just copying everything from our actual main Application file into here
然后我们也需要ShaderProgramSource
and then we need ShaderProgramSource as well
ShaderProgramSource可能就是我实际在这儿创建的结构体
ShaderProgramSource might just be a struct that I actually make up here
在这个类中, 而不是放在头文件
in this class rather than have it in the header file
因为我只想在这儿访问它
because I only want it accessible here
如果我们向上滚动
if we scroll up
我们也要用到其中的一些包含
we're going to have to steal some of these includes as well
所以让我们把它们放在这里
so let's pop them down here
我们当然也需要Renderer
and we definitely need the Renderer as well
好了, 酷, 看起来很不错
okay, cool, so that looks pretty good
当然, 我们现在来清理一下
of course, let's clean this up now
所以我们有ParseShader, 我要创建所有这些方法
so we have ParseShader which I'm gonna make all of these methods
那么我们就有了ParseShader
so we're gonna have ParseShader
我们不需要filepath, 因为在成员中已经有了
we don't need the filepath, because we have that on the member
尽管我可能会把它传过去
although I might pass that in anyway
关于CompileShader, 所以这不再需要是静态的, 看起来不错
compile, so this does not need to be static anymore, that looks good
我们的CreateShader也不需要是静态的
our CreateShader as well will not make that static
我们让它成为Shader类的成员方法, 就像那样
and we'll make it a member Shader, like that
这个可能有点大, 让我把它调小一点
and this is probably a bit big, let me make it a bit smaller
希望你们还能够看到
hopefully you guys can still see
CompileShader也成为类的一个方法, 好了, 那看起来不错
CompileShader becomes a member as well, okay, that looks pretty good
那么让我们开始创建这些实际的方法
so let's start making these actual functions
那么我就把它们放在这里, 我猜是unsigned int CreateShader()
so we have on my make them up here, I guess unsigned int CreateShader
然后我们还有CompileShader
and then we also have CompileShader
这是我想做的, 但它返回一个int
which is what I try to make, but that returns an int
所以我们来编辑一下, 好了, 实际上
so let's edit that, yeah, in fact
我要回去看看我原来的计划
I'm going back on my whole original plan here
实际上是在Application文件中匹配我之前有的
and actually just making a match what I had an Application
因为我忘了, 我有一半的代码, 我们把它也复制一下
because I forgot, I had half of that code, let's copy that as well
这个ParseShader, 我们去掉Shader
for ParseShader, let's get rid of the shader thing
好了, 酷, 这就是我们现在的接口
all right, cool, so that's what our api kind of looks like right now
我们把这个去掉, 这是, 好了, 我们要
and let's get rid of this, and this is, okay, so we're going to
我猜是因为我们这儿有ShaderProgramSource
I guess because we've actually got ShaderProgramSource here
我们确实需要那样做
we kind of do need to have that there
我还是要保持简单, 把这个ShaderProgramSource移到这里
so I'm just gonna again keep it simple, and move this ShaderProgramSource over here
酷, 好了, 那看起来挺不错的
cool, alright, that looks pretty good
当然这里会有错误, 但这没关系
and of course we're getting errors here, but that's fine, okay
现在我们已经把这个代码转换到这个文件中了
so now we've actually converted this code to be inside this file
而不是在Application文件中, 那么让我们把它从Application文件中移除吧
instead of inside Application, so let's remove it from Application
现在我们真正需要做的就是让它运行起来
and now all we really need to do is actually make it work
那么我们需要做的第一件事是在Shader源码中
so the first thing that we really need to do is inside our Shader source code
在构造方法中, 我们只需要设置m_RendererID为compile或者, 抱歉
in the constructor, we're just going to set m_RendererID to be compile or, sorry
它是什么, 所以我们做的第一件事是传递着色器
what is it, so the first thing we do is we pass the shader
让我们返回Application文件中, 看看它实际做了什么
let's go back to Application, actually see what it's doing
所以当来到我们的着色器时, 我们基本上做了所有这些
so when it comes to our shader, we're doing all of this basically
那么这两行代码就是我们需要的
so these two lines are what we need
所以我们得到了source, 然后m_RendererID就是这个
so we get the source, and then m_RendererID is what this is
这就变成了CreateShader, 好了
and that becomes CreateShader, okay
当然, 除了这个
and then of course instead of this
就是filepath, 我们有这样的filepath
filepath, we're gonna have filepath like that
所以我们只是把这个filepath作为成员来维护
so we're really just maintaining this filepath here as a member
但这只是为了调试
but just for debugging purposes
好了, 在析构方法中, 我会调用GLCall(glDeleteProgram())
okay, in the destructor, I'm gonna call GLCall(glDeleteProgram())
然后这就是我们的m_RendererID
and then this is going to be our m_RendererID
现在这是真正相关的, 如果m_RendererID不是0的话
now this is really only relevant, if the m_RendererID isn't 0
所以如果它真的成功地创建了它
so if it's actually successful in creating it
这一切看起来都很好
that all of this looks pretty good
我认为Bind和Unbind
I think Bind and Unbind
当然就是GLCall(glUseProgram(m_RendererID))
of course is just gonna be GLCall(glUseProgram(m_RendererID))
然后Unbind就使用0
and then Unbind is going to use zero
就是glUseProgram(0), 然后就是SetUniform4f
UseProgram zero, SetUniform4f
那么当我们回到我们的Application文件
so if we go back to our Application
我们可以看到它是什么, 就是glUniform4f
we can kind of, well, we can see what it is, glUniform4f
那么就是GLCall(glUniform4f())
so GLCall(glUniform4f())
现在我们需要的是统一变量的位置
now what we actually need here is the location of the uniform
所以我们需要找到统一变量的位置
so we need a way to get the location of the uniform
然后就是v0 v1 v2 v3
and then v0 v1 v2 v3
好了, 这就是GetUniformLocation的作用, 也就是这段代码
okay, and that's where GetUniformLocation comes in, which is just this code here
那么就是GLCall(getUniformLocation(shader, name.c_str()))
so GLCall getUniformLocation and then the name.c_str()
shader是像这样的m_RendererID
and shader is m_RendererID just like that
很好, 酷, 我们实际需要做的是分配这个
okay, cool, so what we need to do here is actually assign this
那么就是unsigned int location=glGetUniformLocation()
so unsigned int location equals glGetUniformLocation
如果location等于-1, 这意味着我们实际上没有它
if location equals -1, it means that we don't actually have it
现在我们可以给这段代码做个断言
now we could just make this code assert here
但有时我们把-1作为一个着色器位置是很有效的
but sometimes it's quite valid for us to actually have -1 as a shader location
例如, 如果我们在着色器中有一个统一变量
so if we have a uniform in our shader for example
它在某些地方被使用, 但是我们注释掉了那一行
and it's being used somewhere, but we comment that line out
或者我们声明了一个统一变量, 但我们只是还没有使用它
or we declare a uniform, but we just don't use it yet
或者出于任何原因
or for whatever reason
那就意味着它被剥离了
then that's going to mean that it gets stripped
这意味着我们在着色器中根本没有统一变量
which means that we don't have that uniform in the shader at all
结果是-1
and this is going to give us -1
但我们可能仍然希望我们的着色器正常工作, 因为
but that might like we still want our shader to work like normal, because
我们可能故意声明了一个统一变量, 但没有使用它
we might have intentionally just declared a uniform, but not used it
这就是为什么我不想在这里断言
so that's why I don't want to assert here
但我们可能想在这里打印一些信息, 比如
but we may want to print some kind of message here, being like
你知道的, warning uniform, 然后是name, 接着是doesn't exist
you know, warning uniform, and then name, doesn't exist
以防我们有一个渲染器错误
just in case we have a redenerer error
这样我们就能看到那个, 然后我们也会返回那个location
so that we can see that, and then we'll also return that location
这将变成GetUniformLocation(name)
now this is going to become GetUniformLocation(name)
这是GetUniformLocation
and this is so GetUniformLocation like that
所以我们的实际函数看起来很好
so our actual function that looks pretty good
只要确保这是v2和v3, 而不是f
just make sure you call this v2 and v3, and not f
出于某种原因, 我不知道我为什么中途换了
for some reason, I don't know why I did that just switched halfway through
但在我们的例子中, 它们是正确的
but they just answer value in our case
好了, 酷, 所以那看起来挺不错
all right, cool, so that was pretty good
现在有一个问题等下会讨论
now there is an issue that will address in a minute
就是GetUniformLocation这个方法
with the GetUniformLocation thing
但除此之外, 我认为这是相当不错的, 我们的代码应该可以运行
but otherwise, I think that's pretty decent, our code should work
那么让我们回到Application文件, 希望我们的代码能运行
so let's actually go back to Application, and hopefully our code does work
我要把所有东西都关掉除了那个
I'm actually gonna close everything but that
好了, 这个东西会变成
okay, so this stuff is going to just become
我们先把Shader包含在顶部, 就是#include "Shader.h"
let's actually include Shader at the top first of all, include Shader.h
然后下面这里, 就是Shader shader(), 我们会接收这个路径
and then down over here, Shader shader, and we'll take in this path
然后我们会调用shader.Bind(), 我们可能就让它那样保持绑定
and then we'll do shader.Bind(), then we can just leave it bound probably
而不是这个location, 以及我们试图设置的那个变量
and then instead of this location, and whatever we're trying to set that variable
这个就变成了shader.SetUniform4f("u_Color")
this just kind of becomes shader SetUniform4f the name which is u_Color
然后实际值就是这儿这个
and then the actual values which is this thing here
然后我相信, 所以你可以看到减少了多少代码
and then I believe, so you can see how much code that reduces
现在它很好很简单
it's nice and simple now
UseProgram(0)就是shader.Unbind()
UseProgram 0 is just shader.Unbind()
有了缓冲区之类的绑定, 我们也可以马上解决这个问题
with bind like buffers, we could probably address that in a minute as well
我们实际上并不
we don't actually
哦, 我们有下一个缓冲, 我们马上就可以做
oh we do have a next buffer we can do that in a minute
glUseProgram(shader)当然就是shader.Bind()
glUseProgram shader of course is just shader.Bind()
这个又是shader.SetUniform4f("u_Color")
and this again which is shader.SetUniform4f("u_Color")
然后是那个
and then that
好了, 所以你可以看到这简化了我们的代码
okay, so you can see how much that simplified our code
最后, 我们根本不需要删除它
and then finally we don't need to delete it at all
因为当我们到达作用域的尽头
because when we actually reach the end of the scope
它将被shader的析构方法删除
it will be deleted by the destructor of shader
好了, 那么有了这个, 我不知道为什么我还留着这个
and yeah, so with this, I don't know why I've still got this
但对于glArrayBuffer, 那就是vb.Unbind()
but glArrayBuffer, that's just vb.Unbind()
然后那个就是ib.Unbind(), 所以我们现在可能修复了那个问题
and then that's just ib.Unbind(), so we might as well fix that now
基本上解除所有的绑定
just unbinding everything basically
我可能就保持那样, 好了, 酷, 那么我们继续, 看起来很不错
I might just leave that like that, okay, cool, so there we go, looks pretty good
让我们来运行一下这个, 看看会发生什么
let's just hit f5 or run this and see what happens
好了, 那么看起来还不错
okay, so it looks pretty good
我们得到了同样的矩形, 颜色也有, 所以一切正常
we get the same kind of rectangle and the colors working, so everything looks fine
那么让我们来说说存在的这个小问题吧
so let's talk about this little problem that we have
所以这并不是什么大问题
so it's not really like a huge issue or anything
但就在Shader.cpp中
but in Shader.cpp
我们这儿实际存在的问题就是在这个GetInformLocation中
what we actually have here is inside this GetInformLocation
每次我们设置这个统一变量
every time we set this uniform
我们实际上一次又一次地获取这个位置
we actually retrieve the location again and again and again
那并不是特别快
and that's not particularly fast
我们真正想做的是缓存它
what we actually want to do with this is cache it
所以我们只能在它们第一次的时候获取到它
so that we only really retrieve it the first time in them
就是这样, 我们完成了, 我们可以很容易地做到这一点
that's it, we're done, and we can do that really really easily
当我们返回Shader.h文件
if we just go back to Shader.h
我会包含unordered_map
I will include something called unordered_map
这只是哈希映射或者哈希表
which is really just a hash map or a hash table
然后我就会这样创建std::unordered_map, std::string, unsigned int
and then I'm just going to make std::unordered_map std::string two unsigned int
就叫这个为m_LocationCache
and then call this m_LocationCache
或者我应该说是m_UniformLocationCache
or specifically m_UniformLocationCache I should say
接下来我要做的第一件事就是检查一下
and then all I'm going to do here is the first thing I want to do is check to see
这个UniformLocationCache实际是否包含这个name
if the UniformLocationCache actually contains the name
所以如果这个不等于m_UniformLocationCache.end()
so if this doesn't equal m_UniformLocationCache.end()
我们就简单返回m_UniformLocationCache[name]
we'll simply return an m_UniformLocationCache and then the name
否则我们就直接去获取这个位置
otherwise we'll go ahead and retrieve the location
如果它不等于-1, 我们实际上就可以缓存它
and if it actually doesn't equal -1, then we can actually cache it
我是说, 严格来说, 我们真的不需要
I mean, technically speaking, we don't really need
就像我们可以缓存它, 即使它是-1
like we could cache it even if it is -1
不像它不会改变, 不管统一变量是否存在
it's not like it's going to change, whether or not uniform exists
直到我们用可能的新代码重新编译着色器
until we actually recompile the shader with potentially new code
所以这个不需要是else
so this doesn't really need to be an else
实际上, 我可以把它从else中移除, 然后无条件添加它
in fact, I might remove this from else, and just add it regardless
所以我们实际上添加了那个position
so we're actually adding that location there
这样的话, 如果我在这里放一个断点
and that way if I just put a breakpoint here
这样我们就能验证它是否正常了
so that we can verify that works properly
在第一次运行这段代码的时候
in the first time that I run this code
我们这儿当然会导致缓存不命中
we should of course result in a cache miss here
实际上会正确地获取位置
and actually retrieve the location properly
您可以看到position为0, 这是一个有效的位置
you can see the location in zero, which is a valid location
然后第二次, 如果我按f5, 我们实际上到这里
and then the second time, if I hit f5, that we actually go here
我们应该只返回这个, 而不需要执行glUniformLocation
we should just return this, without having to do the glUniformLocation
你可以看到那个运行了, 好了, 当然我们在视觉上不会看到任何不同
you can see that that works, okay, so of course we shouldn't see any difference visually
但那应该会给我们提供一个很好的性能提升
but that should provide us with a nice little performance boost
特别是当我们开始有很多统一变量在我们的着色器
especially when we start having a lot of uniforms in our shaders
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
这就是它的全部内容, 和往常一样
that's pretty much all there is to it, as always
你们可以通过patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持这个系列教程
you can help support the series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
你们会获得我今天在这儿写的所有源码
and you'll get access to all the source code that I wrote here today
以及单独的源码, 一集一集的
as well as kind of individual source code, episode per episode
所以一定要去那里帮助支持这个系列
so definitely go help out support the series there
非常感谢所有支持我的人
huge thank you to everyone who does that
因为没有你们, 我们就不会在这儿, 非常感谢大家
because yeah we wouldn't be here without those people, so thank you so much
差不多就这些了
that's pretty much all there is about like
这是一个基本的着色器系统
that is a basic shader kind of system
你可以抽象出来, 我的意思是
that you can abstract out, I mean
你可以把它变得非常非常复杂, 我们肯定会这么做
you can go really really crazily complicated with this, and we will definitely do that
我保证在提到的游戏系列中
I promise in the game mentioned series
但是现在, 对于这个系列来说, 它真就那样了
but for for now, for this series, that's really it
我的意思是, 如果我们很快地回到我们的代码中
I mean if we jump back into our code really quickly
这是我们可以做的, 也是我们必须要做的
another thing we could do and what we'll have to do
实际上是在扩展整个统一变量
is actually kind of extend this whole uniform thing
例如, 如果我们想要设置一个浮点数
so for example, if we wanted to set a single float
那么就是1f, 然后我们要在这里写另一个函数
so 1f, then we'd have to write another function here
它就像这样取我们的值
that actually just takes in our value like this
我把这个函数复制过来
I'll go over here copy this function
因为那就是Uniform1f
cause that Uniform1f
去掉所有这些多余的, 这里也一样
remove all of these extra ones and this here as well
你可以看到, 我们基本上就这样了
and you can see that we basically just
就是这样, 这就是我们实现这些的方法
that's it, that's how we implement this these
我可以逐一检查并实现每一个
and I could go through and implement every single one
包括矩阵和整数, 以及所有这些东西
including the ones for matrices and integers, and all that kind of stuff right now
但我不想让你们觉得无聊
but I don't want to bore you guys
不管怎样你们都明白了
you get the point anyway and
因为我们需要那些SetUniform函数
as we require those SetUniform functions
因为当我们开始使用这些实际值时
because as we start using those actual values
我们会在后面实现它们
we'll have to kind of we'll just implement them as we go along
那样就会很简单
and that way it'll be nice and easy
我们不用花一半的时间来写这些
and we don't have to spend like half now now writing all the ones
因为那将会很无聊, 无论如何, 下次
because that will be really boring, anyway, next time
我认为还有其他是需要抽象的
I think what else is there really to abstract
在某种程度上, 我们必须处理我们的渲染器
we have to deal with our renderer at some point
我不知道下次是不是一定会这样
I don't know if that's necessarily gonna be next time
但是看起来, 其他的东西都被抽象了
but it looks like everything else is pretty much abstracted away
这里我没有看到任何OpenGL代码
I didn't see any OpenGL code here
除了我们实际的绘制调用, 这将由渲染器完成
apart from our actual draw call which which will be done by the renderer
那么让我们下次实现那个吧
so let's do that next time
让我们继续, 抽象我们的渲染, 并实际创建一个渲染类
let's go ahead, and abstract our render, and actually create a render class
可以传递我们创建的所有这些对象
into which we can kind of pass all these objects that we've created
希望它能帮我们渲染一些东西
and hopefully then it will render something for us
并且然后我认为, 在那之后
and then I think, after that
我们可能继续研究纹理和更有趣的东西
we can probably move on to stuff like textures and more exciting things
那么不论如何, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
so anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你们喜欢的话, 就来点赞哟, 为了让我知道, 也可以留言
if you did, you can hit that like button, to let me know, and leave a comment
比如, 这系列很棒, 或者很糟糕,  就这样或者其他你想写的
being like, the series is awesome, or it's terrible, do this instead or whatever you want to write
那就是评论区的作用, 说出你的想法
that's what the comment section is for, speak your mind
下次见, 拜
I will see you next time, goodbye